Guide to the Elmer Eric E. E. Schattschneider Papers, 1901 - 1971 (bulk 1955-1971)
Elmer Eric "E. E." Schattschneider Papers, 1901 - 1971 (bulk 1955-1971)
- Series 4. Subject Files
  - Subject files, general
    - Citizenship Clearing House and Citizenship Education Project, newsletters and programs, 1950-1953 (Folder 23)
    - Conference on Preparing College Men and Women for Politics 1953, programs, documents and typescript, 1953 (Folder 24)
      Includes Schattschneider's draft concerning political parties, 2 p.
    - Congress, clippings, 1969 (Folder 25)
    - Congressional Record Quotes 1950-51, notecards (2 folders), circa 1950s (Folder 26-27)
    - Consent in the Private Sector, notes, undated (Folder 28)
    - Cracks in Southern Solidarity, William Buchanan, typescript of Fall 1956 Antioch Review article, circa 1956 (Folder 29)
    - Democracy, notes, undated (Folder 30)
    - Democracy, notes and clippings, circa 1965-1968 (Folder 31)
    - Dewey/Bricker, clippings (1-2 of 3), 1944 (Folder 32-33)
    - Dewey/Bricker, clippings (3 of 3), 1944 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Election 1937, clippings (2 folders), 1937 (Folder 2-3)
    - Election Results Data, Pennsylvania, 1944 (Folder 4)
    - Elections and the Electorate - Politics, notes and clippings (4 folders), circa 1960s (Folder 5-8)
      Includes 2 untitled corrected typescripts, 4 p. each, and "The Overwhelming Public," typescript, 1 p., in folder 4.
    - Electoral College, notes and clippings, circa 1969-1970 (Folder 9)
    - Equality, clippings, 1969 (Folder 10)
    - The Future of Government, notes and clippings, 1964-1967 (Folder 11)
    - General Theory of Politics, notes, drafts and clippings, circa 1950s (Folder 12)
    - Mr. Gerard's 64 Rulers, clippings, 1930 (Folder 13)
    - Government, clippings (2 folders), 1968-1970 (Folder 14-15)
    - Government and Democracy, notes, undated (Folder 16)
    - Government vs. Business, notes, undated (Folder 17)
    - Higher Education in the United States, Wesleyan History, notes, undated (Folder 18)
    - House of Representatives, clippings, 1940-1941 (Folder 19)
    - How Power is Exercised - Negros, clippings, 1967 (Folder 20)
    - How Power is Used, notes, clippings and drafts, circa 1960s (Folder 21)
      Includes "The Ungovernable World," typescript, 8 p.
    - How to Prevent Organizational 'Dry Rot,' John Gardner, Harpers, October, 1965 (Folder 22)
    - How We Invented the Presidency, notes and clippings (2 folders), circa 1960s-70 (Folder 23-24)
    - Labor/Political Action Committees, clippings (1-6 of 7), 1944 (Folder 25-30)
    - Labor/Political Action Committees, clippings (7 of 7), 1944 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Local Government in Connecticut - Reprints and ephemera, 1960-1967 (Folder 2)
    - Report on Long Lane School [Middletown] Fiscal Years ended June 30, 1951 and 1952 (Folder 3)
    - Old Saybrook [CT] Charter Commission, minutes and drafts, 1966-1968 (Folder 4)
    - Mississippi Election 1944, notes, clippings and ephemera, 1944 (Folder 5)
    - National Conventions, clippings (2 folders), 1930-1932 (Folder 6-7)
    - Notebook, pocket-sized, undated (Folder 8)
    - Notes on Books
      - Abernathy, From Frontier to Plantation in Tennessee, undated (Folder 9)
      - Billington, The Protestant Crusade 1800-1860, undated (Folder 10)
      - Burns, Challenge to Democracy, undated (Folder 11)
      - Carroll, E. M., Origins of the Whig Party, undated (Folder 12)
      - Clark, J. P. The Rise of a New Federalism, undated (Folder 13)
      - Doob, V. L. Propaganda (2 folders), undated (Folder 14-15)
      - Geary, A History of Third Parties in Pennsylvania 1840-1860, undated (Folder 16)
      - Greeley, Horace. Recollections of a Busy Life, undated (Folder 17)
      - Krabbe, The Modern Idea of the State, undated (Folder 18)
      - Lasswell, Politics, undated (Folder 19)
      - Luetscher, G. D. Early Political Machines in the United States, undated (Folder 20)
      - Mosher and Ringsley, Public Personnel Administration, undated (Folder 21)
      - Myres, Party Bolting, undated (Folder 22)
      - Pierce, Public Opinion and the Teaching of History, undated (Folder 23)
      - Reynolds, Machine Politics in New Orleans (2 folders), undated (Folder 24-25)
      - Weed, Thurlow. Autobiography, undated (Folder 26)
      - Zink, City Bosses, undated (Folder 27)
    - Party History Since 1860, notes and collected data, undated (Folder 28)
    - Party Responsibility, notes and clippings, circa 1953 (Folder 29)
    - Party Responsibility, What is Politics About?, Dualism, notes, circa 1960s (Folder 30)
    - Plebiscitary Presidency and Political Parties, notes and drafts (2 folders), undated (Folder 31-32)
    - Political parties: clippings, 1930-1931 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Political parties: clippings, 1930-1939 (Folder 2)
    - Political Personalities, clippings (3 folders), 1932-1939 (Folder 3-5)
    - Population, notes, drafts and clippings, 1965-1967 (Folder 6)
      Includes Population Explosions, typescript, 6 p.
    - Presidency, General, notes, drafts and clippings (2 folders), circa 1960s (Folder 7-8)
    - Presidential Patronage, notes and clippings, circa 1969 (Folder 9)
    - Primary Elections, clippings, 1930 (Folder 10)
    - Private Sector, notes and drafts (2 folders), undated (Folder 11-12)
    - Supreme Court, clippings, 1940-1941 (Folder 13)
    - Teaching and Education, notes, circa 1950s-1960s (Folder 14)
    - Teaching Democracy, notes and clippings, circa 1968 (Folder 15)
      Includes Check list of things to do when making a local political survey, typescript.
    - Two-Party System, notes, drafts and clippings (3 folders), circa 1950s (Folder 16-18)
    - Votes, Elections, Registration, clippings, 1930 (Folder 19)
    - What is Government: notes and clippings, 1960-1967, undated (Folder 20-21)
- Series 5. Citations, Photographs, Miscellany.
  See also Box 13 for oversized photographs.
  - Citations [2], 1957 (Folder 22)
  - Photographs of E. E. Schattschneider as a young man [2], undated (Folder 23)
  - Schattschneider family photographs [11], undated (Folder 24)
  - Group photographs including E. E. Schattschneider [2], circa 1950s-1960s (Folder 25)
  - Other photographs [2], 1945 and undated (Folder 26)
    Includes inscribed portrait, For 'Schatt' with the high regards of Brien McMahon, January 1945.
  - Souvenir of Camp Sherman, Chillicothe, Ohio, illustrated booklet, 1917 (Folder 27)
  - Postcards. 39 black-and-white blank, unsent photo postcards of German cities, circa 1920s-1960s. (Folder 28)
- Series 6. Oversized Documents
  - The American Chief Executive, Joseph Kallenbach, peer review notes and corrected typescript, circa 1965-1966 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - American Government, notes, drafts and clippings, circa 1950s (Folder 2)
  - American Government, notes, drafts and corrected typescripts, circa 1969 (Folder 3)
  - British Origins [of U.S. Government], notes and drafts, circa 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Criticisms of Government, notes, circa 1960s (Folder 5)
  - Democracy, notes, undated (Folder 6)
  - Democracy, notes, drafts and clippings, 1968-1970 (Folder 7)
  - Election Results Data, Pennsylvania, 1944 (Folder 8)
  - Functional Theory of Party Organization/The Agenda of American Government, notes and typescripts, after 1951 (Folder 9)
  - General Theory of Politics, notes, drafts and clippings, circa 1950s (Folder 10)
  - Glorious Revolution, notes and typescript, undated (Folder 11)
  - Government by Consent of the Losers/Majority Rule and Consent, notes and clippings, 1969-1970 (Folder 12)
    Includes copy of Middletown Strike News #5, May 8, 1970.
  - Illinois, quotes from Illinois newspapers concerning the 1944 election, 1944 (Folder 13)
  - Local Government in Connecticut, Old Saybrook Charter Commission, minutes and drafts, 1966-1968 (Folder 14)
  - Notes on Pierce, Public Opinion and the Teaching of History, undated (Folder 15)
  - Republican Party in the South, notes, clippings and correspondence (2 folders), 1944-1945 (Folder 16-17)
  - The Semi-Sovereign People, Chapter 2: Scope and Bias of the Political System, Pressure Politics, notes, drafts and corrected typescripts, circa 1960 (Folder 18)
  - South Carolina, 1944 Election
    Most notes are handwritten transcriptions of newspaper editorials with glosses by Schattschneider.
    - Ballot, notes and clippings, 1944 (Folder 19)
    - The Campaign, notes and clippings, 1944 (Folder 20)
    - Election Returns, notes and clippings, 1944 (Folder 21)
    - Negro Voters, notes and clippings, 1944 (Folder 22)
    - Party Rules/White Primary, notes, 1944 (Folder 23)
    - Poll Tax, notes and clippings, 1944 (Folder 24)
    - Primary and State Conventions, notes, 1944 (Folder 25)
    - Republican Party, notes and clippings, 1944 (Folder 26)
    - Soldier Ballot, notes and clippings, 1944 (Folder 27)
    - Solid South, notes and clippings, 1944 (Folder 28)
    - Southern Democrats, notes and clippings, 1944 (Folder 29)
    - Special Congressional Election, notes and clippings, 1944 (Folder 30)
    - State Senators, notes and clippings, 1944-1945 (Folder 31)
    - White Supremacy, notes, 1944 (Folder 32)
  - Two Hundred Million Americans in Search of a Government
    - Early notes and drafts, circa 1969 (Folder 33)
    - Chapter 1: What Are We Looking For?, notes, drafts and corrected typescripts, 1969 (Folder 34)
    - Chapter 2: Why do People Make Miscalculations About Government?, notes, drafts and corrected typescripts, 1969 (Folder 35)
    - Chapter 5: Why is a Generation a Proper Period of Time for the Study of Politics?, notes, drafts and corrected typescripts, 1969 (Folder 36)
    - Chapter 6: Some Political Words, notes, drafts and corrected typescripts, 1969 (Folder 37)
    - Appendix, drafts, circa 1969 (Folder 38)
  - Two-Party System, notes, drafts and clippings, circa 1950s (Folder 39)
  - Wisconsin, quotes from Wisconsin newspapers concerning the 1944 election (4 folders), 1944 (Folder 40-43)
  - Photographs
    - Family photograph [including Schattschneider in his late teens/early 20s], circa 1910s (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified group photograph of young men, circa 1920s
    - Group composite photo labeled W.H.S. '01 [high school class photo?]
- Series 7. Film and Books.
  - The Meaning of Democracy, E. E. Schattschneider - Republic Steel Corporation - Building Political Leadership, 16mm, sound, 20 minutes, 1960. (Folder 2)
  - Books with annotations by Schattschneider
    - Chapin, F. Stuart. An Introduction to the Study of Social Evolution - The Prehistoric Period. New York: The Century Co., 1913.
    - Garner, James Wilford. Introduction to Political Science. New York: American Book Company, 1910.
    - Hennessy, Bernard C. Political Education and Political Science: The National Center for Education in Politics 1947-1966. Typescript, 1966.
    - Jones, Chester Lloyd. Statute Law Making in the United States. Boston: Boston Book Company, 1912.
    - Lindsey, A. D. The Essentials of Democracy. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1929.
    - McMahon, Arthur W. Congressional Oversight of Administration: The Power of the Purse. New York: Academy of Political Science, 1943. (Box 14)
    - McBain, Howard Lee. Prohibition Legal and Illegal. New York: Macmillan, 1928.
    - Shields, Currin V. A Note on Party Organization: The Democrats in California. Reprinted from The Western Political Quarterly, December 1954.
    - Stedman, Murray S. and Herbert Sontoff. Party Responsibility-A Critical Inquiry. Reprinted from The Western Political Quarterly, September 1951.
    - Stone, Irving. Clarence Darrow for the Defense. New York: Bantam Books, 1958.
    - Trevelyan, George Macaulay. England Under the Stuarts. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1925.
    - Young, Roland. The American Congress. New York: Harper Brothers, 1958.
    - Zinn, Charles J. How Our Laws Are Made. Washington, D.C.: United States Government Printing Office, 1956.